Finding Aid for Sadye Power Papers, 1940-1979
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Sadye Power Papers 1940-1979
Power, Sadye.
2 linear feet
89193 Aa 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan, civic leader, and officer in various cultural, educational, and population control organizations. Files relating to the Planned Parenthood Federation of America, the Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood, the Merrill-Palmer Institute in Detroit, Greenhills School in Ann Arbor, the Alumnae Council of the University of Michigan, and the Ann Arbor Symphony.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Sadye Power (donor No. 4500 ) in 1979.
The collection is open to research.
Sadye Power was a philanthropist and activist on behalf of various social and political causes. Throughout the course of her life, she worked long and hard on such issues as family planning, abortion, child care, urban family life, education, cooperative living, and volunteerism. And like her husband Eugene Power, Sadye Power was a patron of the arts supporting it with contributions and with her time.
Born Sadye Harwick in 1901, Sadye graduated from the University of Michigan in the mid 1920s with a master's degree in psychology. While at the University she met Eugene B. Power, the soon-to-be founder of University Microfilms. They were married on June 27, 1929.
Sadye Power was very active in a variety of women's organizations and causes. In the 1930s, she became involved in the family planning movement probably as an outgrowth of her training in psychology and her interest in counseling and mental health issues. She was long involved in planned parenthood, serving in increasingly responsible positions, notably as member of the board of directors of both Planned Parenthood World Population and Planned Parenthood Federation of America (1969-1975). She also was a member of the Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood, serving from 1963 until the mid-1970s.
Sadye Power's energies were not directed to family planning alone. Beginning in 1940, she served on the board of governors of the Henderson Memorial House, which was established by the University of Michigan Alumnae Council as a cooperative residence for women. During the war years, she participated in volunteer training efforts through the Civilian War Services and helped to organize a Veterans' Counseling Center in Ann Arbor. She was also a founder and member of the board of the Ann Arbor Art Commission and of the Merrill-Palmer Institute in Detroit.
Sadye Power died November 26, 1991 at the age of 90.
Documenting her activities with various local, national, and international organizations, the Sadye Power papers have been grouped into four series: Early Activities, Educational Organizations, Planned Parenthood, and the Arts.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor Symphony.; Birth control.; Civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Greenhills School (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Merrill-Palmer Institute.; Planned Parenthood Federation of America.; Power, Sadye.; University of Michigan. Alumnae Council.; Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood.; Women civic leaders--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Early Activities 1940-1951
  Early Activities (1940-1953; 0.2 lin. ft.) contains materials from Sadye Power's early involvement with the University of Michigan Alumni Association and the Civilian War Services in Ann Arbor. Included are minutes, correspondence, and reports.
  - Henderson Memorial House
    - Alumnae Council of the Alumni Association 1940-1951 (Box 1)
    - Board of Governors minutes 1946-1953 (Box 1)
    - Personnel and Selection Committee minutes 1947-1950 (Box 1)
    - General 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - Civilian War Services 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Ann Arbor Veterans' Counseling Center reports and bylaws 1944-1946 (Box 1)
  - Volunteer Advisory Committee reports and correspondence 1948 (Box 1)
- Educational Organizations 1969-1979
  Sadye Power's participation in two local Educational Organizations (1969-1979; .5 lin. ft.), the Merrill-Palmer Institute of Detroit and the Greenhills School in Ann Arbor, comprise the second series in the collection.
  - Merrill-Palmer Institute 1969-1979
    - General 1975-1976 (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1969-1979 (Box 1)
    - Financial 1969-1979 (Box 1)
    - Minutes, Board of Trustees 1969-1977, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Mothers and Toddlers Project (Power Project) (Box 1)
    - Program Committee
      - Minutes 1969-1974 (Box 1)
      - Background information 1969, undated (Box 1)
    - Proposal for Masters' Degree Program 1973 (Box 1)
    - Research Fellowship Applications 1977-1978 (Box 1)
    - Special Reports 1977 (Box 1)
  - Greenhills School 1976-1978
    - Minutes, Board of Trustees 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Planned Parenthood 1963-1972
  The third series - Planned Parenthood (1963-1979; 1.2 lin. ft.) - is the most substantial and documents Sadye Power's active interest in the condition of women and children. Sadye was involved with Planned Parenthood on the local, regional, national and international level. Her participation in these organizations is represented by minutes, financial documents, annual reports, committee materials, and more.
  - Washtenaw County League for Planned Parenthood
    - Minutes, Board of Directors and Executive Committee 1964-1976, 10 folders (Box 1)
    - Financial Documents 1964-1976, 9 folders (Box 2)
    - Annual Reports 1963-1976, 12 folders (Box 2)
    - Education and Planning Committee 1965-1968 (Box 2)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity Program 1976-1979 (Box 2)
    - Alphabetical file
      - Bibliographies (Box 2)
      - Clippings (Box 2)
      - Correspondence 1967-1975 (Box 2)
      - Newsletters 1966-1973 (Box 2)
      - Policy Statements, Organizational Charts, Statistics (Box 2)
      - Sex Education (Box 2)
  - Great Lakes Regional Council minutes and newsletters 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Planned Parenthood World Population correspondence 1969-1975 (Box 2)
- Arts 1958-1979
  The final series concerns Sadye Power's interest in the Arts (1958-1979; .1 lin. ft.), notably with the Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra and the Ann Arbor Art Commission.
  - Ann Arbor Art Commission 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra
    - Bylaws and articles of incorporation 1970-1976 (Box 2)
    - Financial statements and budgets 1968-1978 (Box 2)
    - Minutes, Board of Directors 1968-1978 (Box 2)